How Should I Think of a Person I Hate?
Hello
(Sunim) Our level of daily happiness
could differ
based on whether we start our day with
a dull mindset or with a clear one.
The weather is same to all, but for those
who watched the weather forecast
and prepared
it wouldn't matter whether
it rains or not
If it rains, they can open up the umbrella
If it doesn't
they could just carry it with them
Those who are prepared can think,
"come what may."
But for those who are not prepared,
rain can be a big problem.
The same applies to life.
Praying today
doesn't guarantee good things
Nor does it bring bad things
Whether you pray or not,
things that are
bound to happen will happen
Things that are not will not happen
But those who pray are prepared.
They can handle whatever comes their way.
Those who are not prepared,
struggle when things happen to them.
There's an old saying that
even when you're attacked by a tiger,
you can survive if you focus your mind.
Even in such dire situations,
you can survive
as long as you put your mind to it.
It means that
we can overcome any situation
as long as we act wisely.
This is why we pray an hour
every morning when we wake up.
Only of those
who pray every morning
have gathered here today
(Audience Laughter)
Now who will ask the first question?
Sunim, it's nice to meet you.
I'm graduating the
Buddhist university next spring
and volunteering for the fall course.
It's been wonderful taking Buddhism class,
and it's been so much pleasure,
volunteering for the fall course.
Lately, at volunteer work,
I found myself going back and forth,
liking and not liking this one person
changing all the time.
I'd like to ask for your advice on
how I could observe those feelings.
(Sunim) What do you mean?
Just observe it.
(Audience Laughter)
Just observe your feelings.
"I like her," "I don't like her,"
"My mind keeps changing."
Just acknowledge
what is going through your mind.
The other person is the same.
But whose mind keeps wandering
back and forth ?
between like and dislike
Are you going back and forth
or is it the other person?
(Questioner) It's me.
Yes, it's you.
What about you keeps changing?
Your thoughts.
What lies at the root of your thoughts?
Your karmic consciousness
Do you understand?
You should notice your thoughts and think,
"Oh, this is my karmic consciousness."
At first,
I just worked hard with great joy.
But these day,
I find myself thinking
(Questioner)
"I really dislike that person."
What's wrong with that?
Don't think you should feel
one way or the another.
You already felt a certain way
There is no right or wrong way to feel it
can you resist the feeling
the way you feel?
when you feel a certain way,
Don't think you should feel
one way or the another.
Just as "I'm judging other people"
Don't conclude that you shouldn't
judge other people
because you practise Buddhism.
Don't judge yourself
for judging others
Just acknowledge that as part of yourself.
"This is me."
"This is not my original nature"
"but my
karmic consciousness is at work here."
"This is how my mind reacts
in response to others."
"This is how I feel
when I see that person."
"This is my karma."
and Just acknowledge it.
Once I acknowledge it,
is that all there is to it?
(Sunim) Yes.
By acknowledging that it's my karma,
can I change my karmic consciousness?
What should you do once you
acknowledge it and want to change?
Then you need to put an effort into it.
(Questioner) How?
Through praying?
When you're angry,
you should first acknowledge
you are feeling the anger, right?
If you're fine with being angry,
you can continue to be angry.
If you feel like
being angry isn't good for you,
then you can tell yourself
you shouldn't be angry next time.
And if you're angry again, then you say
"Ah, I'm still feeling anger."
As you repeat this, your anger decreases.
While I'm able to recognize my anger,
I find it hard not to judge other people.
Hence I wanted to seek your thoughts
on being judgmental.
Judgment is something that happens
based on your standards.
Right and wrong, correct and incorrect is
based on your own view.
Only when there is a standard,
there is right and wrong.
Only when I'm standing, there is
front, back, east, west, south and north.
If there's no me, there is no direction.
Where would you set as a point
when we talk of direction?
What we call the West sea is actually
the East sea from China's standard.
To China it is the East sea
where the sun rises,
yet in Korea it is the West sea
where the sun sets.
We say two different things
about the same sea.
Busan people say Daejeon is in the north,
while Seoul people say it is in the south.
As you see, judgment basically means
we have a standard.
Based on this standard we judge,
and yet what is this standard?
It is our own personal standard.
Judgment is not objective
as it is based on our own standard.
Christians judge
based on Christian standards,
as do Buddhists and Muslims.
Koreans judge based on Korean standards.
From the Korean perspective,
Ahn Jung-geun was a patriot.
Yet from the Japanese perspective,
Ahn Jung-geun was a terrorist.
We say these things
based on our own standards.
Hence judgment is not objective.
You should think to yourself,
"This is how I judge"
"This is how I'm seeing it from my end"
The way you think is
neither right or wrong.
You can't help but think a certain way.
You are the center of your world
after all.
Yet this doesn't necessarily mean
you are right.
Therefore you shouldn't insist on
your point of view.
The fact that you judge is true,
it is what it is.
But you shouldn't insist on it.
Say out loud what you think of
something in a certain way,
or you feel a certain way is fine.
It is you sharing your thoughts.
Yet you shouldn't insist you are right.
You have no basis to argue that.
You are basing your judgment on your own
perspective, your own standard.
You are speaking from your own standpoint.
You are speaking based on your own self.
Think of a scenario where
two people are walking down the street.
The husband is walking in front,
wife is following from behind.
Husband says from his perspective,
"What's taking so long? Hurry up."
The wife says from her perspective,
"Why are you hurrying so much?"
Each speaks from
his or her own perspective.
Hence from the
standpoint of the one behind,
the one in the front is fast.
To the one in the front,
the one behind is slow.
In reality there is
no such thing as fast or slow.
Depending on where we stand,
we say things are fast or slow.
All judgments in this world is
based on such standards.
Because of this we cannot say
anything is objective.
Nothing is objective.
Everything is subjective.
So what does it mean to
let go of a standard?
There is no everlasting, abiding Dharma.
Nothing is one way or the other.
Yet, once you take on a standard
based on a certain condition
there emerges left and right
front and back, right and wrong,
correct and incorrect, good and evil.
You can take on a standard as a Christian,
a Buddhist, or simply as yourself.
While you can take on such standards,
there is no reason
you should insist on it.
You can speak of your own standard.
But you should say
"I see it this way from my point of view."
"I feel a certain way from my end."
(Sunim) Judgment happens,
but you have no reason to hold on to it.
Hence when you find yourself judging,
acknowledge it
by saying
"So this the standard I'm taking,"
"This is my Karma".
If you don't insist on it,
it becomes weaker.
Thank you.
(Sunim) You're welcome.
(Applause)